<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>devops « Plataformatec Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/devops/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Plataformatec&#039;s place to talk about Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Elixir, and software engineering</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 18:59:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Outpost v0.1.0 is released!</title>
		<link>/2011/02/outpost-v0-1-0-is-released/</link>
					<comments>/2011/02/outpost-v0-1-0-is-released/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vinicius Baggio]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 18:41:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[devops]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monitoring tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[outpost]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ruby]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1731</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Outpost is me, scratching my own itch. For a while now, freelancing or working for others, I work with pretty much all the stack in web development: from front-end development with HTML and CSS up to the system administration. And sometimes, I screw up. Sometimes, stuff go wrong. Maybe that Sphinx isn&#8217;t getting indexed or ... <a class="read-more-link" href="/2011/02/outpost-v0-1-0-is-released/">»</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/2011/02/outpost-v0-1-0-is-released/">Outpost v0.1.0 is released!</a> first appeared on <a href="/">Plataformatec Blog</a>.</p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Outpost is me, scratching my own itch. For a while now, freelancing or working<br />
for others, I work with pretty much all the stack in web development: from front-end<br />
development with HTML and CSS up to the system administration.</p>
<p>And sometimes, I screw up. Sometimes, stuff go wrong. Maybe that Sphinx<br />
isn&#8217;t getting indexed or even running after an unsuccessful deploy. Maybe that<br />
background job isn&#8217;t being run, and I forget to verify it.</p>
<p>I know there are excellent tools that already solve this problem. But I wanted an<br />
easy way I would be able to code my own monitoring rules, using one of the<br />
languages I like the most. And also, the fantastic Aaron Patterson (or<br />
tenderlove), one of the most prominent faces of the Ruby community once told in<br />
a Q&amp;A at <a href="http://university.rubymendicant.com/">RMU</a>: it should be fun!</p>
<p>And thus the Outpost idea was born. Outpost is a framework so I can easily<br />
implement Ruby code that query the current state of any service I want. I can<br />
also write code that can go into the database and do a SELECT on a table (a<br />
jobs table, for example) to check if everything&#8217;s fine.</p>
<h3>What is Outpost?</h3>
<p>Outpost is basically a DSL where you can describe rules to monitor your<br />
service, application, server, whatever. Below is a very simple example:</p>
<pre lang="ruby">require 'outpost'
require 'outpost/scouts'

class MyWebPageOutpost < Outpost::DSL
  using Outpost::Scouts::Http => "web page" do
    options :host => 'localhost', :port => 3000
    report :up, :response_code => 200
    report :down, :response_body => {:match => /Ops/}
  end
end</pre>
<p>In this example, we are monitoring (using what I&#8217;ve called &#8216;Scouts&#8217;) HTTP<br />
communication to <code>localhost:3000</code>. It will report that the system is<br />
up if the response code is 200 (HTTP OK) and report that it is down if the<br />
response body contains the word &#8220;Ops&#8221;, by matching a Regular Expression to it.</p>
<p>There is still a lot of work to be done, but I feel it is ready for a very first<br />
release. There are only two Scouts today: HTTP and Ping, but it&#8217;s so<br />
easy to write new ones that I will be releasing a few more in the next<br />
days.</p>
<p>Also, there are only three expectation matchers: response time, response body<br />
and response code. I believe they are able to cover most of the cases, but it is also<br />
very easy to write new expectations.</p>
<p>Below is another example of an Outpost, based on the integration tests:</p>
<pre lang="ruby">require 'outpost'
require 'outpost/scouts'

class ExamplePingAndHttp < Outpost::DSL
 using Outpost::Scouts::Http => 'master http server' do
   options :host => 'localhost', :port => 9595, :path => '/'
   report :up, :response_body => {:match => /Up/}
 end

 using Outpost::Scouts::Ping => 'load balancer' do
   options :host => 'localhost'
   report :up, :response_time => {:less_than => 500}
 end
end</pre>
<p>For more details, please check the <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.github.com/vinibaggio/outpost">project&#8217;s README, on GitHub</a>.</p>
<h3>The future</h3>
<p>My plans for Outpost are: SSH support, so you can connect to servers that do<br />
not expose their services to the outer world, a very simple web dashboard to show<br />
the results, better error reporting (for now you can only know which Scout<br />
failed, but not why), a script that automatically generates Outposts for Rails<br />
apps, and the list goes on!</p>
<p>Crazy idea: wouldn&#8217;t it be nice to have a script that reads Outposts and<br />
tells if a machine is ready to be in production? TDD for machines? Woot!</p>
<h3>Thanks</h3>
<p>This project was my personal project for RMU (Ruby Mendicant University) and<br />
so I would like to thank all the people involved for the amazing experience and<br />
reviews on the project. Also thanks to my friends for listening me nagging<br />
about this project for a while. Finally, thanks to Tomás D&#8217;Stefano, who<br />
did some work on my previous attempt to write Outpost, your work won&#8217;t be<br />
thrown away.</p>
<h3>Closing</h3>
<p>Please share your thoughts about this project. I would love to know your opinion!</p><p>The post <a href="/2011/02/outpost-v0-1-0-is-released/">Outpost v0.1.0 is released!</a> first appeared on <a href="/">Plataformatec Blog</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/2011/02/outpost-v0-1-0-is-released/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
