<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>railsconf « Plataformatec Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/railsconf/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Plataformatec&#039;s place to talk about Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Elixir, and software engineering</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 19:48:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>PlataformaTec at RailsConf 2011!</title>
		<link>/2011/05/plataformatec-at-railsconf-2011/</link>
					<comments>/2011/05/plataformatec-at-railsconf-2011/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vinicius Baggio]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 17:05:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[railsconf]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2111</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This year me and José Valim had the pleasure of going to Baltimore, in the US, to one of the biggest Rails events of the world! RailsConf is definitely the best place to have the opportunity of meeting and talking to a lot of great Rubyists and Railers, and also attending their talks. Not only ... <a class="read-more-link" href="/2011/05/plataformatec-at-railsconf-2011/">»</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/2011/05/plataformatec-at-railsconf-2011/">PlataformaTec at RailsConf 2011!</a> first appeared on <a href="/">Plataformatec Blog</a>.</p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">This year me and José Valim had the pleasure of going to Baltimore, in the US, to one of the biggest Rails events of the world! RailsConf is definitely the best place to have the opportunity of meeting and talking to a lot of great Rubyists and Railers, and also attending their talks.</p>
<p>Not only that, we also participated (though briefly) in BohConf, the official RailsConf unconference, which was great and very well organized! The talks covered a myriad of topics, guided the exploration on some technologies and counted with the presence of the Ruby Mendicant University students. José Valim presented a tutorial on his own <a rel="nofollow" href="https://github.com/josevalim/elixir">Elixir</a>, showing how to build a chat server using some cool stuff that both Elixir and Erlang provide. The code used on the tutorial is available on <a href="https://github.com/josevalim/elixir-websockets-demo">Valim&#8217;s GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>Also, José Valim presented a talk on the ongoing Rails refactoring, guiding through the SOLID Principles and the changes in rails&#8217; own code. You can get the slides at <a href="http://en.oreilly.com/rails2011/public/schedule/detail/19579">his RailsConf page</a>. While you&#8217;re at it, please rate and give your feedback if you watched it live!</p>
<p>In this edition of RailsConf, DHH presented the &#8220;assets revolution&#8221; part of Rails 3.1 and why CoffeeScript was adopted. It doesn&#8217;t matter if you&#8217;re into CoffeeScript or not, Rails now has amazing internals to deal with assets, raising them as &#8220;first-class citizens&#8221;. You can have this on the latest Release Candidate that was released last week. The keynote is available on <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cGdCI2HhfAU">Youtube</a>.</p>
<p>Regarding Keynotes, RailsConf 2011 had amazing ones. I strongly recommend you to watch <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IVBVZGfzkVM">Eric Reies&#8217; Lessons Learned</a>, regarding delivering products and learning from your mistakes, from his upcoming book with the same title.</p>
<p>Tenderlove (or sometimes known as Aaron Patterson) presented a very good talk about database query caching and proposed a future Rails refactoring to restructure the rack middleware stack in order to make it better and faster. A must watch talk! Check it on Youtube: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?=vIVBVZGfzkVM">Aaron Patterson&#8217;s Double Dream Hands: So Intense!</a> (fast forward to minute 40 or so for a surprise)!</p>
<p>The talks themselves were good, in general. Highlights, in my opinion, are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://en.oreilly.com/rails2011/public/schedule/detail/18051">Aman Gupta&#8217;s Rails Performance Tools</a> was the first time I saw Aman Gupta&#8217;s presentation live. Even though he got his slides from other conferences, I have to say I was very impressed. He really knows what he is talking about and the examples were very applicable to everyday&#8217;s work. You definitely should check it out.</li>
<li><a href="http://en.oreilly.com/rails2011/public/schedule/detail/17762">Jim Weirich and Matt Yoho&#8217;s Securing your rails application</a> began slowly, showing easy-to-avoid security issues, but it picked up nicely, showing live examples on how to replicate the security issues described, very cool!</li>
<li><a href="http://en.oreilly.com/rails2011/public/schedule/detail/19434">Joe Ferris&#8217; Testing the Impossible</a> was a very good talk. At PlataformaTec we always discuss the best ways to test code and it was very nice to see someone else&#8217;s effort on the subject, I was able to confirm some ideas and learn new ones!</li>
<li><a href="http://en.oreilly.com/rails2011/public/schedule/detail/18047">Yehuda Katz&#8217; Building Rails Apps For the Rick Client</a> explained why Rails is much more than simple view helpers and then moved on to discuss API implementations. The proposed <a href="https://github.com/drogus/bulk_api">bulk api</a> was particularly interesting and is a good example of a private protocol between the client (SproutCore) and server side (Rails) for advanced transactions and performance!</li>
</ul>
<p>All in all, it was a great RailsConf! I had a blast, meeting people and having drinks at the parties was also one of the best parts of the conference! And what about you? What is your opinion about RailsConf, did you like it? Which were your favorite talks?</p>
<p>See you in 2012!</p><p>The post <a href="/2011/05/plataformatec-at-railsconf-2011/">PlataformaTec at RailsConf 2011!</a> first appeared on <a href="/">Plataformatec Blog</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/2011/05/plataformatec-at-railsconf-2011/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2010 &#8211; A year in review</title>
		<link>/2010/12/2010-a-year-in-review/</link>
					<comments>/2010/12/2010-a-year-in-review/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vinicius Baggio]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 17:18:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[devise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dsl]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[euruko]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rails]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[railsconf]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[responders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rubyconf]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[show_for]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[simple_form]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1612</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This year is coming to an end and it was amazing for us at Plataforma Tecnologia. We are proud to share with you, faithful reader, our accomplishments in 2010, which weren&#8217;t few. Open Source The year has begun on fire. In February, José Valim made his way into the Rails Core team and has been ... <a class="read-more-link" href="/2010/12/2010-a-year-in-review/">»</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="/2010/12/2010-a-year-in-review/">2010 – A year in review</a> first appeared on <a href="/">Plataformatec Blog</a>.</p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This year is coming to an end and it was amazing for us at Plataforma Tecnologia. We are proud to share with you, faithful reader, our accomplishments in 2010, which weren&#8217;t few.</p>
<h3>Open Source</h3>
<p>The year has begun on fire. In February, <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.org/2010/2/13/jos-e-valim-and-carl-lerche-joins-rails-core">José Valim made his way into the Rails Core team</a> and has been doing a great work since then, including many contributions to the Rails 3 release.</p>
<p>We are also really proud with <a href="http://www.github.com/plataformatec/devise">Devise</a>. It got very mature, achieving the 1.0 version this February. Since then, Devise is becoming one of the best solutions for authentication in Rails and also one of the most watched repositories on GitHub. </p>
<p>In August, <a href="/2010/08/devise-1-1-is-out-and-ready-to-rock-with-rails-3/">Devise 1.1</a> was released with Rails 3 support and a bunch of cool features. Recently, a lot of work is being done towards the 1.2 version, which includes full support to the awesome <a href="http://www.github.com/intridea/omniauth">OmniAuth</a> gem.</p>
<p>We also released <a href="http://www.github.com/plataformatec/simple_form">SimpleForm</a> this year. SimpleForm is our take on building forms in a simplified way lead by Carlos Antônio who recently did a great work on HTML 5 support.</p>
<p>Other gems were released, such as <a href="/2010/03/show-your-objects-baby/">ShowFor</a>, which is a DSL to simplify how you show your objects in views and also <a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/responders">Responders</a>, a collection of Rails 3 responders.</p>
<h3>Book</h3>
<p>Eariler this month, José Valim&#8217;s book entitled <a href="http://plataformatec.com.br/crafting-rails-applications/">Crafting Rails Applications</a> has been released by the highly acclaimed publisher <a href="http://www.pragprog.com/">Pragmatic Bookstore</a>! The book covers internal aspects of Rails 3 and how you can bend it to your will. The reviews and buzz has been great so far, even though still in beta. <a href="http://plataformatec.com.br/crafting-rails-applications/">Grab your copy now!</a></p>
<h3>Events</h3>
<p>This year was also very productive in terms of events. We&#8217;ve been to a lot of events, heck, George was even able to go to RailsConf, in Baltimore! Also, José Valim has spoken in various events, including <a href="/2010/06/dsl-or-nodsl-at-euruko-2010/">Euruko 2010 (includes video)</a>, <a href="http://vimeo.com/17088248">RubyConf Brazil 2010 (talk in portuguese)</a> and OxenteRails 2010. </p>
<p>Carlos, Hugo and George did their share as well, speaking at various events, from smaller and user-group events to bigger ones such as OxenteRails, RS on Rails and QCon SP.</p>
<h3>Company</h3>
<p>The company itself is getting more mature and increasing. At January 2010, PlataformaTec was composed of 6 people, and up until December 2010, 5 other people joined the company (including myself)! We also have started playing with iOS development, something we believe to have a great future, expect future blog posts on the subject.</p>
<h3>Great 2011!</h3>
<p>Have a great New Year! We wish you all the best for year to come. We have high expectations for 2011, so stay tuned!</p><p>The post <a href="/2010/12/2010-a-year-in-review/">2010 – A year in review</a> first appeared on <a href="/">Plataformatec Blog</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/2010/12/2010-a-year-in-review/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
